Critical Thinking

Fill-in-the-Blank

Read each item carefully and then complete the statement by filling in the missing words.

1. Your appearance should be neat and ________ .

2. Medical information about a patient is ________ and should be shared only with other medical personnel who are involved in the care of that patient.

3. The four basic goals of EMR training are to know what not to do, know how to use the EMR life support kit, know how to ________, and know how to ________ other EMS clinicians.

4. Firefighters or ________ ________ personnel are likely to be the first responders in most emergencies.

5. A(n) ________ ________ ________ ________ or ________ ________ ________ ________ usually receives the telephone call reporting an incident.

Short Answer

Complete this section with short written answers using the space provided.

1. What are the 11 standard components of an EMS system?

2. After dispatch, what are the three points of patient contact with the EMS system?

3. What are the four major goals of EMR training?

4. Why is it important to have medical oversight?

5. Name any five items that should be included in an emergency medical responder life support kit.

6. List the six components of quality improvement identified by the Institute of Medicine.

7. Identify five questions you should consider when evaluating a person whom you suspect is involved in human trafficking.

You Make the Call

The following scenario provides an opportunity to explore concerns associated with patient management. Read the scenario and answer the question to the best of your ability.

1. You are dispatched to an emergency scene and gain access to the patient. You complete the primary assessment and stabilize the patient, and then paramedics arrive on the scene to assist. What should you do next?

Critical Thinking

Fill-in-the-Blank

Read each item carefully and then complete the statement by filling in the missing words.

1. Stress management consists of recognizing, preventing, and ________ stress.

2. Scientific studies show that most people need about ________ hours of uninterrupted sleep per night.

3. ________ stress education provides information about stresses that you will encounter and reactions you may experience.

4. On-scene ________ support and disaster support services provide aid on scenes of especially stressful incidents.

5. A(n) ________ ________ ________ ________ is used to alleviate stress reactions caused by high-stress emergency situations.

6. Federal safety standards require approved ________ ________ any time you are working on an active highway.

7. ________ objects may include vehicles, trees, poles, buildings, cliffs, and piles of materials.

8. Because electricity is ________, make sure that electrical ________ has been turned off by a(n) ________ person.

9. Latex and nitrile medical gloves can help prevent the spread of disease from blood contamination, but they provide no protection against ________ ________.

10. Weather cannot be ________ or ________.

Short Answer

Complete this section with short written answers using the space provided.

1. List three foods that provide a steady energy source over a prolonged period.

2. List five signs or symptoms of stress.

3. Describe four standard precautions recommended by the CDC.

4. List three things you should keep in mind when parking your vehicle at an emergency scene.

5. What five special rescue situations require special safety considerations, training, or equipment?

6. List five hazards that may be present at an accident scene and need to be considered by the EMR.

7. Name the five stages of the grieving process.

You Make the Call

The following scenarios provide an opportunity to explore concerns associated with patient management. Read the scenario and answer the question to the best of your ability.

1. At 4:00 am, you are dispatched to a shooting at a residence. As you approach, two police cars leave the scene of the crime with their lights and sirens on, and dispatch informs you that law enforcement personnel believe the shooter has left the scene. What should you do?

2. You respond to a call for a “sick person” at an apartment complex known for violence and frequent drug overdoses. When you arrive, you find a 35-year-old man standing in the doorway of his apartment. The patient is pale with sweaty skin. He tells you that he has been feeling ill for several days. He complains of night sweats, weight loss, and coughing up blood-streaked sputum for several days. The apartment complex is rather crowded and dirty. What should you do?

Critical Thinking

Fill-in-the-Blank

Read each item carefully and then complete the statement by filling in the missing words.

1. The primary technique used to move a patient onto a long backboard is ________ ________.

2. Use backboards to ________ patients who have neck or back injuries.

3. ________ ________ are used to minimize excess movement of the neck and head.

4. A(n) ________ stretcher or orthopaedic stretcher is a rigid device that is helpful in moving patients out of small spaces.

5. ________ cervical collars do not provide sufficient support for trauma patients.

6. When performing a log roll, the rescuer holding the patient’s ________ should always give commands to move the patient.

7. Because the log-rolling maneuver requires sufficient space for ________ rescuers, it is not always possible to perform it correctly.

8. A(n) ________ ________ is used when a wheeled stretcher cannot be moved into a small space.

9. The ________ ________ ________ is used to move a patient who is on the ground or the floor onto an ambulance stretcher.

10. Your top priority is to ensure your own ________.

Short Answer

Complete this section with short written answers using the space provided.

1. Name two of the most common reasons why you would move a patient.

2. What should you do if you suspect that a patient has sustained trauma to their head or spine?

3. Why would the recovery position be used for an unconscious patient who has not sustained trauma?

4. Describe three situations that require moving a patient before emergency medical care is provided.

5. Name three pieces of equipment that EMS clinicians commonly use for lifting and moving patients.

6. Name five guidelines to keep in mind when deciding to move a patient.

You Make the Call

The following scenarios provide an opportunity to explore concerns associated with patient management. Read the scenario and answer the question to the best of your ability.

1. You and your partner are directed to an older adult who lives in a house near a major fire. He says that he has a heart condition and gets out of breath after walking a few steps. What should you do?

2. Your unit arrives at the scene of a motor vehicle crash involving a car striking a tree. The patient tells you she lost control of her vehicle after answering her cell phone. She complains of neck pain. There appear to be no life threats or safety concerns for you or the patient. Your partner calls for a transporting EMS unit. What should you do?

Critical Thinking

Fill-in-the-Blank

Read each item carefully and then complete the statement by filling in the missing words.

1. A(n) ________ ________ states the types of medical care a person wants or wants withheld if the person is unable to make their own treatment decisions.

2. Injuries caused by improper care can be a situation of ________.

3. For a Good Samaritan law to provide any protection from civil liability, you must act in ________ ________ to provide care to the level of your training and to the best of your ability.

4. The ________ ________ ________ is the manner in which you must act or behave.

5. ________ consent is based on the assumption that the patient has the right to determine what will be done to their body.

6. A(n) ________ is a person who has not reached the legal age designated by a particular state.

7. A(n) ________ ________ ________ ________ for health care allows individuals to designate another person to make decisions about medical care for them if they are unable to make decisions for themselves.

8. ________ is the acronym for the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act of 1996.

9. Most personal health information is ________ and should not be released without the patient’s permission.

10. Documentation should be clear, concise, ________, and ________.

Short Answer

Complete this section with short written answers using the space provided.

1. Which agency developed education standards for EMRs?

2. What is the purpose of Good Samaritan laws?

3. What four conditions can be used to reliably determine that a patient is dead?

4. Name three crimes that are reportable.

5. Name three factors that should be included in documentation.

You Make the Call

The following scenarios provide an opportunity to explore concerns associated with patient management. Read the scenario and answer the question to the best of your ability.

1. You are called to the scene of a fight in a bar where a patron reportedly has been stabbed. You consider it a potential crime scene. What should you do?

2. You respond to a home for a “cardiac arrest.” When you arrive, you are greeted by a woman who appears to be in her 80s. She is crying and tells you she believes her husband is dead and says that she did not know what to do. She says she knew this day would come ever since her husband was diagnosed with terminal cancer 3 months ago. As you approach the patient, you notice that he is pale, unresponsive, and does not appear to be breathing. You quickly ask the woman about an advance directive or a DNR. She tells you she believes something like that was done when her husband was in the hospital, but she is not sure. She asks you to do everything you can to keep him alive. What should you do?

Critical Thinking

Fill-in-the-Blank

Read each item carefully and then complete the statement by filling in the missing words.

1. Two types of suction devices are ________ and ________.

2. If a patient is breathing adequately, you can keep their airway open by placing the patient in the ________ position.

3. During inadequate breathing, the patient may experience ________, a change in skin color to blue or gray around the lips or fingernail beds.

4. The most critical sign of inadequate breathing is ________ ________.

5. To perform rescue breathing, pinch the patient’s ________ with your thumb and forefinger.

6. The main purpose of the respiratory system is to provide oxygen and to remove ________ ________ from the lungs.

7. Without oxygen, the brain will die in ________ to ________ minutes.

8. In cases of severe head trauma, a(n) ________ airway may cause further brain damage.

9. ________ ________ occurs when air is forced into the stomach instead of the lungs.

10. Before insertion of an oral airway, the proper size must be determined by measuring from the patient’s ________ to the corner of the ________.

Short Answer

Complete this section with short written answers using the space provided.

1. Name two primary purposes of an oral airway.

2. List the steps involved in inserting an oral airway.

3. List the steps involved in inserting a nasal airway.

4. List the steps involved in ventilating a patient with a mouth-to-mask device.

5. Name two signs of inadequate breathing.

6. Name two types of airway obstructions.

7. Describe how to place a patient in the recovery position.

You Make the Call

The following scenarios provide an opportunity to explore concerns associated with patient management. Read the scenario and answer the question to the best of your ability.

1. You are called to a scene where an unconscious 18-year-old has choked on a piece of food and has a severe airway obstruction. You treat this patient by performing CPR. What would you have done differently if this patient had been conscious when you arrived?

2. You are dispatched to a local church for a possible cardiac arrest. When you enter the room, you find a 72-year-old man lying on the floor, surrounded by people. The patient has a tracheal stoma and does not appear to be breathing adequately. A woman from the church tells you that she would have started mouth-to-mouth CPR but was unsure how to proceed due to the stoma. What should you do?

Critical Thinking

Fill-in-the-Blank

Read each item carefully and then complete the statement by filling in the missing words.

1. Chest compressions for an infant should be delivered at a rate of at least ________ to ________ per minute during CPR.

2. An infant’s pulse should be checked at the ________ artery.

3. The circulatory system consists of a(n) ________ , a network of pipes (blood vessels), and ________.

4. The main artery carrying blood away from the heart is the ________.

5. ________ ________ is the temporary stiffening of muscles that occurs several hours after death.

6. Bloating of the stomach is called ________ ________.

7. Most out-of-hospital cardiac arrest patients have an irregular heart electrical rhythm called ________ ________.

8. A patient in ________ ________ is unconscious, has no carotid pulse, and is not breathing.

9. Brain damage begins within ________ to ________ minutes after the patient has gone into cardiac arrest.

10. You should regularly update your skills by successfully completing a recognized ________ course.

Short Answer

Complete this section with short written answers using the space provided.

1. Where along the sternum should you place your thumbs to deliver chest compressions to an infant?

2. Name two causes of gastric distention during CPR.

3. Name the four major arteries discussed in this chapter.

4. What are four reliable signs of death?

5. What are situations that you should be alerted to before operating an AED on a patient, and how do you correct them?

6. List six reasons for discontinuing CPR.

7. What are three signs that effective CPR is being administered to the patient?

You Make the Call

The following scenarios provide an opportunity to explore concerns associated with patient management. Read the scenario and answer the question to the best of your ability.

1. You arrive on the scene to find a 58-year-old man lying facedown in his garden next to a tiller he has been operating. He does not respond to you as you approach. In fact, you think he is not breathing. What should you do?

2. You respond to check on the well-being of an older woman at the request of her neighbor. The neighbor tells you that the woman is usually out in her garden every day without fail, but she has not been seen for several days. After gaining access to the woman’s residence, you find her lying supine in bed. There is a foul odor in the room, and you notice that she is unresponsive. Your primary assessment reveals no breathing and no pulse. You observe a purplish coloring on her back. What should you do?

General Knowledge

Matching

Match each of the items in the left column to the appropriate definition in the right column.

________ |

1. Redirection

|

A. Abnormal thought processes and/or loss of contact with reality

________ |

2. Situational crisis

|

B. A means of focusing the patient’s attention on the immediate situation or crisis

________ |

3. Emotional shock

|

C. Act of rephrasing a patient’s statement to show that they are being heard and understood

________ |

4. Critical incident stress debriefing (CISD)

|

D. State of emotional upset or turmoil caused by a sudden and disruptive event

________ |

5. Behavioral emergency

|

E. A pattern of decline in mental function

________ |

6. Posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD)

|

F. State of shock caused by sudden illness, accident, or the death of a loved one

________ |

7. Empathy

|

G. Ability to sense another person’s emotions

________ |

8. Dementia

|

H. System of psychological support designed to reduce stress on emergency personnel after a major incident

________ |

9. Restatement

|

I. Abnormal behavior that is unacceptable or cannot be tolerated by the patient, family, or community

________ |

10. Psychotic behavior

|

J. Mental health or behavioral condition triggered by experiencing or witnessing a terrifying event

Multiple Choice

Read each item carefully and then select the one best response.

________ 1. Which of the following is NOT one of the phases of a situational crisis?

A. Anger

B. Remorse

C. Empathy

D. Emotional shock

________ 2. You arrive at the scene of a motor vehicle crash and find a teenage girl staring at other emergency personnel caring for an older woman. She then says, “If I hadn’t asked her to take me to the mall, this wouldn’t have happened.” What phase of a situational crisis is this girl probably experiencing?

A. Anxiety

B. Denial

C. Remorse

D. Emotional shock

________ 3. Which of the following should you NOT do when talking to a patient?

A. Establish eye contact.

B. Bring yourself to the patient’s level.

C. Talk in a calm, steady voice.

D. Tell the patient that everything will be all right if it will make the patient feel better.

________ 4. Which of the following is NOT true regarding behavioral emergencies?

A. They may be caused by situational stress or physical trauma.

B. They are not caused by injuries such as head trauma.

C. They call for appropriate communication, especially body language.

D. They describe situations where people behave in an abnormal and unacceptable manner.

________ 5. Behavioral emergencies are caused by:

A. eating excessive carbohydrates.

B. situational stresses.

C. minor trauma, such as an abrasion.

D. rapid breathing.

________ 6. A person who is experiencing high anxiety is likely to exhibit all of the following characteristics, EXCEPT:

A. a loud or screaming voice.

B. flushed face and general agitation.

C. rapid breathing and rapid speech.

D. a calm demeanor and even tone of voice.

________ 7. Which of the following is NOT true when responding to a potentially violent patient?

A. A person who is pacing or cannot sit still is likely to become violent.

B. A person’s posture is not an accurate means of assessing violence potential.

C. Loud, obscene, or bizarre speech indicates emotional instability.

D. When all interventions fail, law enforcement may need to be summoned.

________ 8. Which of the following is NOT typically considered before applying force to restrain a patient?

A. Type of abnormal behavior exhibited

B. Size, strength, and sex of patient

C. Approval from medical control

D. Type of restraint

________ 9. Management of a suicide crisis includes:

A. making judgmental statements.

B. ignoring threats.

C. assuming the patient always acts this way.

D. support of the patient’s ABCs as needed.

________ 10. Warning signs of increased risk of suicide include each of the following, EXCEPT:

A. talking about feeling hopeless.

B. withdrawing from social contact.

C. acting anxious or agitated.

D. hoarding belongings.

________ 11. Which of the following statements regarding dealing with death and dying is NOT true?

A. Dealing with your own feelings is not necessary when comforting others.

B. Do not make false statements about the situation.

C. Do whatever you can to meet the patient’s medical needs.

D. Consider the psychological needs of the patient and family.

________ 12. Which of the following is NOT true regarding dealing with an armed patient?

A. If you are confronted by an armed person, immediately attempt to defend yourself.

B. It is not your role to handle this situation unless you are a law enforcement officer.

C. Do not proceed into an area where there may be an armed person without assistance from law enforcement.

D. If you must wait for law enforcement, stay in your vehicle in a safe location.

________ 13. The suicide rate is highest among people ages:

A. 15 to 25 years.

B. 85 years and older.

C. 45 to 65 years.

D. 65 years to 85 years.

________ 14. Traumatic events that may lead to PTSD include each of the following, EXCEPT:

A. physical attack.

B. sexual assault.

C. working around sick people.

D. military combat exposure.

True/False

If you believe the statement to be more true than false, write the letter “T” in the space provided. If you believe the statement to be more false than true, write the letter “F.”

________ 1. In your role as an EMR, you should give psychological and emotional support to patients, as well as emergency medical care.

________ 2. When a person cannot cope with sudden or unexpected events, the person may act strange or even demonstrate dangerous behavior.

________ 3. As an EMR, you will rarely intervene in a situational crisis.

________ 4. Your interest in helping someone can be communicated by establishing eye contact.

________ 5. Even in serious situations, you can reassure a patient and still be honest by saying that everything possible is being done to help the patient.

________ 6. Standing above a patient with your hands on your hips assures the patient that you are a confident, caring professional.

________ 7. Simple acts of kindness, such as offering a tissue or blanket, can often comfort a person who is emotionally upset and can sometimes lessen the severity of the crisis reaction.

________ 8. If you have negative feelings about a patient, you should not provide care for that patient.

________ 9. The best way to avoid violence against EMRs is prevention.

________ 10. Head injuries and shock may cause behavioral emergencies.

________ 11. High fevers and excess cold may cause behavioral emergencies.

________ 12. Psychotic behavior is characterized by defective or lost contact with reality.

________ 13. A state of emotional upset or turmoil caused by a sudden and disruptive event is called psychotic behavior.

________ 14. A person who is in emotional shock will not exhibit any physical signs of other types of shock.

________ 15. In a situational crisis, when a patient expresses denial, it is the responsibility of the EMR to quietly but firmly keep repeating reality.

________ 16. During a situational crisis, a person calls you incompetent and swears at you. You should immediately leave the scene and call your supervisor.

________ 17. Anger is difficult to handle objectively because it may seem to be directed at you personally.

________ 18. Treatment of a patient who is exhibiting abnormal behavior does not require the same steps of the patient assessment sequence as treatment of other patients.

________ 19. The EMR should not try to communicate with a patient who is exhibiting abnormal behavior.

________ 20. Effective communication with a patient requires body language that exhibits empathy and interest.

________ 21. Crisis intervention techniques may include touching the patient.

________ 22. Crisis intervention techniques include good eye contact and a calm, steady voice.

________ 23. In crisis management, the most important step you can take is to talk with the person.

________ 24. A good way to reassure a patient and show that you understand is simply to say, “I know what you mean” or “I know how you feel.”

________ 25. Empathy can best be expressed by telling the patient that you know exactly how they feel.

________ 26. The technique of redirection may call for movement of the patient.

________ 27. If the presence of too many emergency personnel at the scene is adding to a patient’s anxiety, it is the responsibility of the EMR to ask them to move to another location.

________ 28. Crowds that may become hostile are the responsibility of law enforcement officers, not the EMRs.

________ 29. EMRs should identify themselves to the patient and give reassurance that they are there to help.

________ 30. If you suspect abuse, your responsibility is to maintain the safety of yourself and the patient.

________ 31. The tension phase is usually the shortest part of the abuse cycle.

________ 32. There should always be an escape route between you and the patient at scenes that may become dangerous.

________ 33. Your ability to use good interpersonal communication skills will help prevent many situations from becoming violent.

________ 34. Depression is more common in older adults than in other age groups.

________ 35. Not all suicide attempts need to be taken seriously.

________ 36. PTSD is a severe form of anxiety.

________ 37. When treating a patient who was sexually assaulted, encourage them to bathe and use the restroom.

________ 38. Coping with the death of others is a routine aspect of your job as an EMR.

________ 39. If you let stress build up without releasing it in healthy ways, it can begin to have negative effects on you and your performance.

________ 40. CISD teams may be helpful to rescuers who have been through an overwhelming or stressful event.

Critical Thinking

Fill-in-the-Blank

Read each item carefully and then complete the statement by filling in the missing words.

1. Every emergency creates some sort of a(n) ________ ________ for the patient and for those close to the patient.

2. ________ is a normal human response to emotional overload or frustration.

3. ________ can help focus the patient’s attention on the immediate situation.

4. Trying to put yourself in the patient’s shoes is known as ________.

5. Many suicide attempts are really ________ ________ ________.

6. Performing simple ________ ________ may help reduce a patient’s anxiety when there are many people around.

7. Abuse has been described as a(n) ________-part cycle.

8. Your most important assessment skill may be your ability to ________ with the patient.

9. There are ________ emotional phases to each situational crisis.

10. ________ and a sense of helplessness can often build to anger.

Short Answer

Complete this section with short written answers using the space provided.

1. List five main factors that can cause behavioral changes.

2. What are some principles you should use when assessing patients with a behavioral problem?

3. What is the proper patient assessment sequence for a patient with a behavioral emergency?

4. Identify five signs and symptoms of child abuse.

5. Name four factors that increase the risk of violence in the workplace.

6. What are three key components of caring for a patient with dementia?

7. List at least three signs and symptoms of extreme stress.

8. What is the purpose of CISD?

9. Provide a response to each of the following statements using the technique of restatement. In addition to rephrasing the statement to show that you understand, try to add some reassuring or encouraging words.

A. From a woman who has been hit by a car: “I can’t stay here! I have to go home and start dinner for the kids!”

B. From the driver of the car that hit the woman: “I didn’t mean to hit her! She just ran out all of a sudden! What if she dies?”

C. From one of the woman’s children, who was with her but not struck by the car: “I want my mommy! Let me go to my mommy!”

10. Provide a response to each of the statements in Question 9 using the technique of redirection.

A. ____________________________________________________

B. ____________________________________________________

C. ____________________________________________________

You Make the Call

The following scenarios provide an opportunity to explore concerns associated with patient management. Read the scenario and answer the question to the best of your ability.

1. When you arrive on the scene, you find a 24-year-old woman pacing the room and crying loudly. When you approach her, she pushes you away, saying, “I don’t want your help; nobody can help me.” She then turns her back to you and continues to pace. According to her friend, she and her boyfriend had a big fight, and he just left. What should you do?

2. You respond to the scene of a suspected suicide. When you arrive on the scene, you are greeted by a neighbor who tells you she found the patient in her closed garage, sitting in her car with the engine running. She said the patient was crying and stated, “I don’t really want to die, but I just can’t deal with this anymore.” After you verify the engine is shut off and the garage doors are open, you approach the patient, a 36-year-old woman. How are you going to manage this patient?

General Knowledge

Matching

Match each of the items in the left column to the appropriate definition in the right column.

________ |

1. Drowning

|

A. A condition in which the internal (or core) body temperature falls below 95°F (35°C) after prolonged exposure to cool or freezing temperatures

________ |

2. Frostbite

|

B. A form of shock that occurs from significant fluid loss and electrolyte loss due to heavy sweating after heat exposure

________ |

3. Heat cramps

|

C. Process of experiencing respiratory impairment from submersion in liquid

________ |

4. Heat exhaustion

|

D. Injury resulting from being beneath the surface of water or another liquid

________ |

5. Heatstroke

|

E. A condition in which the body’s mechanisms for heat release are overwhelmed due to a rapidly rising internal temperature

________ |

6. Hypothermia

|

F. Muscle spasms that usually occur after vigorous exercise in hot weather

________ |

7. Laryngospasm

|

G. Spasm of muscles of the larynx or vocal cords resulting in an inability to breathe

________ |

8. Submersion injury

|

H. Freezing of the skin and deeper tissues caused by exposure to cold

Multiple Choice

Read each item carefully and then select the one best response.

________ 1. Immediate emergency medical care for a patient who has heatstroke should consist of:

A. calling for help.

B. arranging for rapid transport to the hospital.

C. giving the patient a drink of cool water and then treating for shock.

D. maintaining the patient’s ABCs and then lowering their body temperature as quickly as possible.

________ 2. Which of the following statements is true regarding the treatment of mild shock caused by heat exhaustion?

A. Monitoring the patient’s ABCs is usually not necessary.

B. The patient should be soaked in cold water.

C. The patient should be given a drink of cool water unless they are unconscious, nauseated, or vomiting.

D. The patient’s feet and legs should not be elevated.

________ 3. Which of the following signs and symptoms is associated with hypothermia?

A. Agitation

B. Sleepiness

C. Bright red skin

D. Elevated body temperature

________ 4. Your first step in caring for a patient with hypothermia should be to:

A. treat the patient for shock.

B. give the patient something to eat and drink.

C. help the patient walk around to produce more body heat.

D. move the patient to a warmer location and remove any wet clothing.

________ 5. In a patient who is suffering from hypothermia, the heart may stop functioning at what core body temperature?

A. 83°F (28°C)

B. 90°F (32°C)

C. 95°F (35°C)

D. 97°F (36°C)

________ 6. The signs and symptoms of dizziness, nausea, profuse sweating, and a weak pulse indicate:

A. heatstroke.

B. heat exhaustion.

C. hypothermia.

D. heat cramps.

________ 7. The symptoms of hot and flushed skin, loss of consciousness, and high body temperature are indications of:

A. heatstroke.

B. heat exhaustion.

C. hypothermia.

D. heat cramps.

________ 8. Which of the following statements regarding frostbite is NOT true?

A. It may occur on the face.

B. Wind speed may be a factor.

C. Age, exhaustion, and hunger may increase susceptibility.

D. It occurs only after an extended exposure to cold in an outdoor environment.

________ 9. If a person’s body is not able to produce enough energy to keep its core temperature at a satisfactory level, the person has:

A. hypothermia.

B. superficial frostbite.

C. deep frostbite.

D. heat exhaustion.

________ 10. A patient’s symptoms include shivering, sleepiness, and feeling cold. These symptoms indicate:

A. deep frostbite.

B. superficial frostbite.

C. hypothermia.

D. heat deprivation.

________ 11. Which of the following statements regarding drowning is NOT true?

A. Drowning is the second-leading cause of injury and death among children 5 to 14 years old.

B. Alcohol consumption is not a contributing factor in drowning incidents involving teenagers.

C. Young children can drown in liquids as shallow as 6 inches.

D. The process of drowning progresses through several stages.

________ 12. When you encounter a person who has been submerged in cold water for an extended time:

A. do not begin CPR until the core temperature rises to above 95°F (35°C).

B. begin rescue breathing, but do not attempt CPR until an AED is available.

C. CPR should be started and continued until the patient is delivered to an appropriate medical facility.

D. CPR should be initiated if the submersion lasted less than 15 minutes.

________ 13. Which of the following statements regarding electrical injuries from a lightning strike is NOT true?

A. All patients should be transported to a medical facility.

B. Lightning strikes can result in internal burns.

C. Lightning strikes can cause cardiac irregularities or cardiac arrest.

D. Cardiac problems are only seen within the first hour after the strike.

________ 14. Which of the following statements regarding the assessment of a patient with an environmental emergency is NOT true?

A. It is typically best to collect a medical history on the patient before you perform a secondary assessment.

B. You do not need to complete a patient assessment if the patient seems aware of their problems.

C. Review the dispatch information to help decide on the possible treatment for the patient’s problem.

D. The SAMPLE history format will help collect the information you need to provide effective medical care.

________ 15. Which of the following is NOT a sign or symptom of a submersion injury?

A. Diarrhea

B. Vomiting

C. Respiratory distress

D. Coughing

True/False

If you believe the statement to be more true than false, write the letter “T” in the space provided. If you believe the statement to be more false than true, write the letter “F.”

________ 1. Older adults and persons who are exhausted or hungry are more susceptible to frostbite.

________ 2. A person must be exposed to cold for a long time to sustain frostbite injuries, even on very cold, windy days.

________ 3. In cases of frostbite, exposed body parts actually freeze.

________ 4. In the first stage of superficial frostbite, the exposed body part becomes pale white.

________ 5. If a person with frostbite has been out in the cold for hours, you should arrange for transport to the hospital rather than trying to rewarm the affected body parts yourself.

________ 6. As an EMR, your emergency medical care of frostbite will consist of rewarming affected body parts and treating the patient for signs of shock.

________ 7. Although you should never rub a frostbitten area with snow or ice, rubbing the area with your hands or a cloth is a good way to rewarm the area.

________ 8. The core body temperature of a person with hypothermia is lower than normal.

________ 9. Hypothermia occurs only in conditions of extreme cold.

________ 10. You should remove all wet clothing from a person who has hypothermia.

________ 11. Left untreated, hypothermia is serious but rarely fatal.

________ 12. If a patient who has hypothermia is conscious, you should give the patient something warm to drink.

________ 13. If possible, you should move a patient who has hypothermia to a warmer place.

________ 14. If a patient goes into cardiac arrest as a result of hypothermia, you should immediately begin CPR.

________ 15. A person with hypothermia who may have been considered dead for hours can sometimes be revived in a hospital.

________ 16. Heatstroke may cause brain damage or death.

________ 17. The most important step in treating heatstroke is rehydration.

________ 18. Frostbite and hypothermia may be encountered at any time of the year.

________ 19. Exercise, age, and medications may all be factors in a heat-related illness.

________ 20. A patient showing indications of heat exhaustion should not be moved until the ABCs are monitored and the BP is stabilized.

________ 21. A patient with deep frostbite should be transported to a medical facility for treatment.

________ 22. If a patient who appears to have hypothermia stops shivering, it is safe to assume that the patient has recovered and needs no treatment.

________ 23. CPR should be used on hypothermic patients even if there are no vital signs to indicate life.

________ 24. All patients who have sustained a submersion injury should be examined by a physician.

________ 25. The mammalian diving reflex increases the heart rate and metabolic rate while decreasing the body’s demand for oxygen.

Critical Thinking

Fill-in-the-Blank

Read each item carefully and then complete the statement by filling in the missing words.

1. Identify each of the following signs and symptoms associated with heat exhaustion or heatstroke by writing “HE,” “HS,” or both in the space provided.

________ A. Low blood pressure

________ B. Light-headedness or dizziness

________ C. High body temperature

________ D. Profuse sweating

________ E. Altered mental status or unconsciousness

________ F. Flushed, dry skin

________ G. Weak pulse

________ H. Nausea

2. Drinking ________ ________ is an excellent treatment for patients experiencing heat exhaustion.

3. ________ is defined as respiratory impairment because of submersion in water or other fluids.

4. There have been cases in which a person was submerged in cold water for over ________ minutes and was still successfully resuscitated.

5. For someone who is drowning, the feeling of panic produces a(n) ________ breathing pattern.

6. For children ages 5 to 14 years, most drownings occur in ________ and ________.

7. As the body temperature drops and hypothermia progresses, ________ stops.

8. Do not try to warm a frostbitten area by ________ with your hands.

9. One way to help cool a patient is to place ice packs on the patient’s ________.

10. In heatstroke, the patient’s body temperature rises until it reaches a level at which brain ________ occurs.

Fill-in-the-Table

Fill in the missing parts of the table.

Comparing Heat Exhaustion and Heatstroke
Heat Exhaustion | Heatstroke
________ body temperature | ________ body temperature
________ | ________ skin (usually)
________ and ________ skin | ________ and ________ skin
Dizziness and ________ | Altered ________ ________

Short Answer

Complete this section with short written answers using the space provided.

1. Name four body parts most susceptible to frostbite.

2. List the four common signs and symptoms of heat exhaustion.

3. Explain why older adults are more susceptible to heat and cold injuries.

4. What are the steps involved in treating a patient with heatstroke?

You Make the Call

The following scenarios provide an opportunity to explore concerns associated with patient management. Read the scenario and answer the question to the best of your ability.

1. You are at a family reunion at a local community park. You hear a cry for help down by a stream and find a young girl screaming that her brother fell in the stream and cannot swim. When you get near the stream, you see a young boy facedown in the water. He is not moving. What should you do?

2. You respond to a local church festival on a community service detail. Shortly after your arrival, you are summoned to one of the food stands to help a man who is ill. There you find a 62-year-old man with cold, sweaty skin who complains of dizziness and nausea. The ambient temperature outside is 88°F (31°C), and it is much warmer inside the food stand. How should you treat this patient?

Critical Thinking

Fill-in-the-Blank

Read each item carefully and then complete the statement by filling in the missing words.

1. Using the rule of nines, calculate the percentage of the body that would be burned in each scenario for an adult patient.

________ A. Both legs

________ B. Groin, front of trunk, and head

________ C. One-half of the front of the trunk and one arm

________ D. Backs of both arms and back

________ E. Fronts of both legs and groin

2. Use of a(n) ________ is indicated only in situations where extremity bleeding cannot be controlled by direct pressure or elevation.

3. If you get blood on your hands, ________ it off as soon as possible with ________ and ________.

4. Most deaths from gunshot wounds result from ________ blood loss.

5. If an entire body part is torn away, the wound is called a(n) ________ amputation.

6. It is important to stop bleeding as quickly as possible using the ________ dressing available.

7. A(n) ________ is an object placed directly on a wound to control bleeding and prevent further contamination.

8. Two types of bandages commonly used in the field are ________ ________ and triangular bandages.

9. Once you have completed applying the bandage, ________ it so that it cannot ________.

10. Severe scalp lacerations may be associated with ________ ________ or even ________ injury.

11. A nosebleed with no apparent cause is called a(n) ________ nosebleed.

12. If a patient is vomiting blood, it may be an indication of bleeding from the ________ or ________.

13. Injury to the genitals can often result in severe ________.

14. All bites carry a high risk of causing ________.

15. If blisters are present with a burn, be very careful not to ________ the blisters.

16. When dealing with a chemical burn, you should ________ ________ any dry chemical on the patient’s clothes or skin.

17. Chemical burns to the eyes can cause extreme ________ and severe injury.

18. Electricity causes major ________ damage, rather than ________ damage.

Short Answer

Complete this section with short written answers using the space provided.

1. Name three primary parts of the circulatory system.

2. Name three primary causes of shock.

3. Name three things you could use for an occlusive dressing.

4. What are the three classifications of burns?

5. What should you use to cover the affected area after a thermal burn has cooled?

6. Name three signs or symptoms of respiratory burns.

7. What are the steps for the general treatment of shock?

8. What are the steps for treating an open abdominal wound?

You Make the Call

The following scenarios provide an opportunity to explore the concerns associated with patient management. Read the scenario and answer the question to the best of your ability.

1. When you arrive at the scene, you find that your patient is a 6-year-old girl who was preparing breakfast to surprise her mother. She started water boiling, and when she attempted to pour it into a mug, the pan slipped, and the boiling water burned her abdomen, the lower part of her left arm, and the front of both legs. Most of the burn area is covered with large blisters. Some of the blisters are intact, whereas others are broken, with the skin peeling. What should you do?

2. You are dispatched to a local machine shop to check on a man with an injured arm. You are on the scene in less than 1 minute because you are one block away. As you arrive, you are told that the patient got his arm caught in a lathe and has a severe laceration and damage to his lower arm. Upon examination, you note blood spurting from the patient’s lower arm. What should you do?

Critical Thinking

Fill-in-the-Blank

Read each item carefully and then complete the statement by filling in the missing words.

1. Splinting of the cervical spine is accomplished with a rigid ________ and a long or short spine board or backboard.

2. The primary danger in severe facial injuries is ________ of the airway.

3. One sign of a head injury, known as the ________ sign, is a bruise behind one or both ears.

4. A spinal cord injury may paralyze respiratory muscles and cause the patient to breathe using only the diaphragm, which is known as ________ breathing.

5. Fracture of three or more ribs in at least two places causes a condition known as ________ chest.

6. ________ is abnormal brittleness of bones in older people caused by loss of calcium.

7. For a patient with a spinal cord injury, you should not move the patient unless it is necessary to perform ________ or remove the person from a dangerous situation.

8. Three basic types of splints are rigid, soft, and ________.

Short Answer

Complete this section with short written answers using the space provided.

1. Name four primary functions of the skeletal system.

2. Name three major types of injuries to the musculoskeletal system.

3. Name four signs of injury you should look for during a visual examination of a limb.

4. What two questions should you ask a patient who has a limb injury?

5. Name two ways to check for adequate circulation in an injured limb.

6. Name three key signs and symptoms of a spinal injury.

7. Name four things you should always check on an injured limb, both before and after splinting.

8. What are the steps for splinting a forearm injury with a SAM splint?

9. Describe three types of MOI, and give an example of each type.

10. Describe how you would splint an injury to the elbow.

11. Describe four signs or symptoms of a head injury.

12. Describe the treatment for a head injury.

13. List three signs or symptoms of extremity injuries.

You Make the Call

The following scenarios provide an opportunity to explore concerns associated with patient management. Read the scenario and answer the question to the best of your ability.

1. You are dispatched to the scene of a “long fall.” When you arrive, you find a 26-year-old man lying in the snow next to a ladder leaning against the house, and Christmas lights are hanging from the front of the house. His right leg is deformed. What should you do?

2. Your unit is dispatched to an altercation at a local bar. When you arrive, you see one man sitting outside the bar with a towel on his head. You notice the towel is covered with blood. The patient tells you he was struck in the head with a beer bottle. The bartender tells you that two men were fighting in the bar and that one of the men left the scene before your arrival. What should you do?

Critical Thinking

Fill-in-the-Blank

Read each item carefully and then complete the statement by filling in the missing words.

1. The ________, or afterbirth, draws nutrients from the wall of the mother’s uterus.

2. Your primary purpose is to ________ in the delivery of the newborn.

3. A(n) ________, also called a spontaneous abortion, is the delivery of an incomplete or underdeveloped fetus.

4. In the event of ________ births, another set of labor contractions will begin shortly after the delivery of the first infant.

5. Any newborn weighing less than 5 pounds or delivered before 36 weeks of pregnancy is considered ________.

Short Answer

Complete this section with short written answers using the space provided.

1. Describe the three stages of labor.

2. List four questions you should ask yourself when deciding if there is enough time to reach the hospital before delivery.

3. What is the appropriate procedure for putting on sterile gloves?

4. Name three important steps of care after a miscarriage.

You Make the Call

The following scenarios provide an opportunity to explore concerns associated with patient management. Read the scenario and answer the question to the best of your ability.

1. You arrive on scene and find a 32-year-old woman who tells you she is 8½ months pregnant. This is her fifth pregnancy, and she is afraid she will not be able to make it to the hospital in time. She tells you her last labor lasted less than 2 hours. She is having frequent contractions. What should you do?

2. You arrive at the scene of a 27-year-old woman complaining of severe abdominal pain. The patient denies being pregnant, although she reports that she missed her last menstrual period. The patient is pale, with a rapid pulse and decreased blood pressure. What is most likely wrong with this patient, and what is the proper treatment?

Critical Thinking

Fill-in-the-Blank

Read each item carefully and then complete the statement by filling in the missing words.

1. Most ________ facilities are responsible for dispatching fire, police, and EMS.

2. During the response to the scene, keep all equipment secured so that it does not ________ someone in the event of a sudden stop or crash.

3. Control the flow of traffic to ensure the safety of the rescuers, patients, and ________.

4. ________ can provide lifesaving transport to an appropriate medical facility for patients with serious injuries.

5. ________ are red signal flares and should not be used to mark a landing zone because they create a fire hazard.

Short Answer

Complete this section with short written answers using the space provided.

1. List six safety steps you should follow when working around an EMS helicopter.

2. What are the guidelines (the “DO NOTs”) associated with helicopter operations?

You Make the Call

The following scenarios provide an opportunity to explore concerns associated with patient management. Read the scenario and answer the question to the best of your ability.

1. You arrive at the scene of a motor vehicle crash involving three vehicles. There are multiple patients with injuries. As several other EMRs are triaging patients, one of the responders yells for you to dispatch a helicopter and set up a landing zone. What actions should you take?

2. You are the first to arrive at an intersection where a motor vehicle crash has just taken place. A crowd has gathered, and traffic seems to be stopped in both directions. You notice large debris in the roadway from vehicles and see fluids leaking as well. How should you handle this scene?

Critical Thinking

Fill-in-the-Blank

Read each item carefully and then complete the statement by filling in the missing words.

1. At a swimming pool, dock, or supervised beach, a(n) ________ device may be available.

2. The four steps of a water rescue are reach, throw, ________ , and go.

3. If you are involved in a water rescue situation, your primary concerns for the patient must be to open a(n) ________, establish breathing and circulation, and stabilize spinal cord injuries.

4. When turning a patient in the water, make sure to stabilize the ________ and ________.

5. In confined space rescues, you must be careful of hazards, including insufficient ________ and the danger of collapse.

6. In farm rescues, reporting of the emergency may be ________.

7. When you see a person struggling in the water, your first impulse may be to ________ in to assist them, but this is a mistake.

8. If a swimmer has experienced ________ ________, quickly stabilize the head and neck, and then remove the patient from the water.

9. Assume that every vehicle involved in a crash is ________, unless you have manually ________ it.

10. When providing initial emergency care during vehicle extrication, leave the patients in the vehicle unless it is on ________ or they are otherwise in immediate danger.

11. The ________ route must be large enough to permit the safe removal of a packaged patient.

12. The third step in the extrication process is to ________ ________ to the patients.

Short Answer

Complete this section with short written answers using the space provided.

1. List, in order, the four steps you should follow when attempting a water or ice rescue.

2. Name three common signs or symptoms of diving injuries.

3. List four confined spaces that you might encounter as an EMR.

4. What are two deadly hazards you may face when involved in a confined space rescue?

5. What are the seven steps of extrication?

You Make the Call

The following scenarios provide an opportunity to explore concerns associated with patient management. Read the scenario and answer the question to the best of your ability.

1. You are dispatched to a farm for an injured person. When you arrive, you find the patient in a farm silo. He has fallen about 15 feet from the top of the silo and appears to be unconscious. A coworker of the patient says he thinks he had a heart attack. What should you do?

2. You are the first unit to arrive at the scene of a motor vehicle crash. As you approach the scene, you notice that the engine compartment of one of the involved vehicles is on fire and that two passengers are trapped inside. What should you do?

Critical Thinking

Fill-in-the-Blank

Read each item carefully and then complete the statement by filling in the missing words.

1. A(n) ________ of ________ ________ is any agent designed to bring about mass death, casualties, and/or massive damage to property and infrastructure.

2. An agent used to produce a concussion that destroys property and inflicts injury and death is a(n) ______.

3. A personal ________ measures the amount of radioactive exposure received by an individual.

4. Anthrax and smallpox are examples of ________ agents.

5. A(n) ________ period is the time between a person’s exposure to a disease organism to the time the symptoms appear.

6. The ________ triage system is designed to help you find the most seriously injured patients.

7. The ________ ________ ________ lists the most common hazardous materials, their four-digit identification numbers, and the proper emergency actions to control the scene.

8. A(n) ________ ________ is a contaminated area where people can be exposed to sharp metal edges, broken glass, toxic substances, lethal rays, or the ignition or explosion of hazardous materials.

9. Patients requiring urgent care are identified with a(n) ________ tag during the triage process.

10. A person who has died receives a(n) ________ tag during the triage process.

Short Answer

Complete this section with short written answers using the space provided.

1. List five categories of chemical agents.

2. Name four symptoms of exposure to an organophosphate insecticide or nerve agent.

3. Name three common signs of acute radiation sickness with low exposure.

4. What are the signs and symptoms of cyanide exposure?

5. Name five key points to communicate when declaring a disaster.

6. What does the acronym START stand for?

7. What are the five major benefits of the ICS?

You Make the Call

The following scenarios provide an opportunity to explore concerns associated with patient management. Read the scenario and answer the question to the best of your ability.

1. You respond to a frantic call from dispatch stating that white powder has been found at a downtown post office. You respond within a minute of dispatch and arrive 3 minutes later to find several employees screaming and running around with small particles of white powder on their clothes. What should you do?

2. You are the first to arrive at a scene involving a motor vehicle crash between two cars and a bus. There are multiple people walking around with obvious injuries. The bus is on its side, and there is smoke coming from the engine compartment. What should you do?